[ narrator ] Ladies and gentlemen ,
the motion picture you are about to see contains an evil spell ,
as used by practitioners of witchcraft for centuries .
Even today in many parts of the world people practice black magic and witchcraft .
Charms , amulets , voodoo candles , grave dirt , and locks of hair
are believed to ward off evil spirits and spells .
You may doubt the effectiveness of these spells , but
through every civilization people have believed in witches .
Could they all be wrong ?
I don 't think so .
For I have seen its power proved too many times .
I am now about to dispel all evil spirits
that may radiate from the screen during this performance .
Oh , creator of Hecate , Damkina , Marduk 's messenger ,
Tem , Khepera , Ra , Khnemu ,
Beelzebub in the netherworld ,
Satan in Gehenna ,
controller of the seven thousand
and seven curses and talismans ,
and who is known to obedient disciples as Gangida ,
hold all your powers and those of your do-bidders ,
and their familiars ,
and cast a protecting shield above those gathered here present .
Pull back from airy bodies those vested with evil .
Grant , oh , magnificent one , no harm from the spells about to be witnessed .
Direct them not . This faithful servant begs for thy favor .
[ speaking foreign language ]
And now , with a free mind and a protected soul ,
we ask you to enjoy Burn , Witch , Burn .
[ Norman ] I do not believe .
I do not believe .
So , to recap . Four words necessary to destroy the forces
of the supernatural witchcraft .
Superstition , the psychic , etcetera , etcetera .
And these quote are , " A morbid desire to escape from reality . "
Unquote . And can only exist in an atmosphere of belief .
Belief is vital .
Deprived of that acceptance , it reveals itself as another
futile attempt to control one 's environment and the forces of nature .
Each day , science ...
Do you include domestic superstitions like ,
walking under ladders , or the third match ,
or people who wear good luck charms ?
Well , they 're all based on primitive beliefs .
While actually denying any belief ,
people guard themselves by saying there may be something in it .
And so they wear protections .
I think it depends on how personal the belief is .
A friend of mine in the Air Force used to carry a lock of his wife 's hair
under his flying helmet for good luck .
Did it work ?
No , he was killed .
So , each day , science , founded on years of research and truth ,
emerges with feats which put our old-fashioned magicians to shame .
Aladdin rubbed a lamp and a genie appeared .
Today we can press a button and the whole of mankind is obliterated .
[ school bell ringing ]
Well , there 's magic for you .
The disappearance of another hour .
Miss Abbott . Will you collect the test papers for me ?
Yes , Professor Taylor .
[ Norman ] Mr. Jennings !
No paper ?
No paper .
Try pressing a button . Maybe one will appear .
I might press the button that removes you from the class .
See that you read and outline chapter six
and chapter seven over the weekend .
And chapter seven goes for the rest of you .
Thank you , Margaret . Have a nice weekend .
I shall be busy with chapter seven .
It 's a very short chapter , Miss Abbott . And a very long weekend .
Well , you certainly made a fool of yourself .
You didn 't do so badly , either .
Sitting there , mooning at Taylor all through the lecture .
It just so happens that I admire him .
Anything wrong with that ?
Not at all .
But there 's a very thin line between admiration and infatuation .
Oh , don 't be so stupid .
- Have a nice weekend . - Thank you , sir . Good night .
Norman !
Mmm-hmm ?
Are we still for bridge at your house tonight ?
Of course . It 's Friday . I 'd forgotten . Sure , why not ?
Oh , Evelyn thought Tansy might still be under the weather .
No , no , no . She 's fine . Came back from the cottage last night .
Good , good . Well , I don 't know .
Friday night never seems the same without a game of bridge .
- [ Norman ] Hi , Evelyn ! - Come on , Harvey .
Right . Well , about 8 : 00 then ?
Fine .
Bridge is on .
It infuriates me to think that
Taylor might be selected for promotion before you .
The scholastic average of his students
is better than that of any other professor .
Including your husband ?
I didn 't make any exceptions , Evelyn .
Well , he 's made very rapid strides here .
The fact is , Norman and Tansy are newcomers .
We play bridge with them , we work together ,
but we still don 't accept them .
Well , I could never accept a woman like Tansy .
She doesn 't seem to be interested in anything .
She spends most of her time at that cottage of theirs .
It 's a logical excuse to avoid getting involved with us
and our committee teas .
- I wish I had one . - Oh , rubbish !
We 've contributed more to this college in 15 years
than Taylor could give in a lifetime .
Just because he manages to charm better grades out of his idiot students ,
you and Lindsay stand to be pushed aside .
Nobody 's being pushed aside , Evelyn .
Taylor hasn 't been appointed yet .
Darling !
[ cat meowing ]
It 's you .
Tansy !
[ Tansy ] Coming !
Hi .
Hey , you 're supposed to act interested .
Wasn 't I ?
One day I shall burn all your stuffy old books .
They invade every corner of our lives .
You know what ?
You need rest . Or some excitement .
I 'm not quite sure which .
I 'll settle for dinner .
Oh , how I hate these Friday nights .
It won 't be that bad .
I am sorry , darling , I can 't help it , but these women make me nervous .
Oh , they 're all right .
You know , Norman , I can cope with many things ,
but not with petty scholars and their jealous , bickering wives .
It 's all a question of adjusting .
Well , I try . So help me I try .
But when you have a middle-aged Medusa like Evelyn Sawtelle
hissing away at the thought of your gaining a chair in sociology .
I wish I was as certain as you are .
Oh , you 'll get it .
Evelyn knows it , Harvey knows it and Sister Flora knows it .
And those three make a solid majority .
And what about Hilda Gunnison ?
Stuck with her devoted Harold and resenting the fact that he openly admires you .
Harold does ?
It 's true , Norman . Quite true .
- You know what I wish ? - Hmm ?
I wish we were three thousand miles
and two years away from this place .
Jamaica . A field trip .
We could breathe .
Jamaica also had its malaria and its poverty .
You 're an incurable romantic .
You 're pining for that old warlock , Carubius
and his phony black magic .
Don 't scoff , Norman .
A male witch .
That 's what 's wrong with you .
He 's cast his spell over you .
You 're enchanted .
And you are .
- Harvey. - [ Harvey ] Yes , dear ?
You 've trumped my ace .
Off with his head .
It would be off with mine , Lindsay , if I 'd done it to you .
Next time , Evelyn , try some of your hypnosis on Harvey .
Plant the suggestion to play only the right cards .
How is the hypnosis , Evelyn ?
Planning to put the entire board under
and make them give Harvey the chair ?
Lindsay , just play .
[ softly ] Did I say something ?
Yes , dear , you said something .
Go on , Lindsay .
Yes , quite . The rest are mine .
Oh , I knew it .
I think we ought to take up hypnotism , darling .
We might get a rubber occasionally .
You can 't have everything . Not even by hypnosis .
You can hypnotize the bad , but you can 't hypnotize the cards .
[ Lindsay ] It 's simply a question of remembering
how the last hand was played .
How the packs got together .
How the shuffle habits of the dealer disarranges the factors
according to the bids .
[ laughing ] And , well , there you are !
And where exactly is that ?
Where I always suspected . Lindsay has put a jinx on the cards .
Lindsay , what have you been keeping from me ?
[ laughing ]
I always suspected Lindsay was a dark horse .
Well , I think it 's time for a snack .
Oh , that 's a bewitching thought !
We are not through , yet .
Oh , don 't hurry . I have to put the coffee on .
We 'll help you .
Twelve hundred it is .
Does that mean us , too ?
You 've forgotten the cups .
When do they decide about the chair , Norman ?
Early next week , I think .
Do you think you 'll beat out my brother-in-law ?
Lindsay , just eat .
I think I will , they look delicious .
You don 't really deserve it , you know .
- Oh ? - You 've got too much already .
A beautiful wife , this lovely house and that cottage by the sea .
Your excellent thesis and your ability to interest the students .
Now what 's the answer to it all , eh ?
Have you sold your soul to the devil ?
- [ clattering ] - Careful , Tansy !
- Well ? - Heart and soul . Here she is . My good luck charm .
[ Lindsay ] You certainly seem to lead a charmed life , I must say .
Old Lindsay can have his theory . I 'll stick to hypnotism .
Good heavens , look at the time .
I 've got a lot of work to catch up on in the morning .
Have you lost something ? Tansy ?
What ?
I said , have you lost something ?
Oh , yes . A shopping list .
Make another .
Well , there was a phone number on it .
A dressmaker that I wanted .
It hasn 't jumped in there , has it ?
No .
You 'll find it in the morning .
Well , I 'm off .
I 'll be up in a moment , darling .
Tansy !
What ?
Where are my pajamas ?
They 're in the wash . Get a clean pair .
What are you doing ?
Where did this come from ?
What is that doing on the bed , Norman ?
Well , mine got stuck , so I had to move yours .
What about this ?
It 's a souvenir .
Of what , for heaven 's sake ?
Of our stay in Jamaica .
It was a gift from Carubius .
Something to remember him by ?
He wanted me to have it .
It certainly looks like him . Is that the only reason why you 'd keep it ?
Do I need a better one ?
It 's supposed to mean something , isn 't it ?
Of course , darling .
It 's a good luck charm . That 's why you 're so successful .
Come on , dearie , time to go to bed . After all , three is a crowd .
Did you find your list ?
No . I 'll make another .
[ doorbell ringing ]
- Cleaners . - Oh , good morning .
Thank you .
Okay , thanks .
Oh , wait a minute , will you ?
[ gasps ]
Next Thursday afternoon will be all right , sir ?
- Yeah , sure . Thanks . - Good day .
Well ?
Well , what , darling ?
- I have to put these away . - In a moment .
- I want to get lunch , Norman . - In a moment .
[ laughing nervously ]
- You look so grim . - What 's the meaning of all this ?
I simply must put these away , Norman .
All right , what do you want ?
The truth .
I told you . They 're souvenirs .
The truth !
All right . I was trying to use conjure magic .
Trying to work spells ! Trying to change the future !
That 's what you really want to hear , isn 't it , Norman ?
That 's exactly what I don 't want to hear .
Then believe what I told you last night .
About one dried up spider , yes , but not all that rubbish !
Graveyard dirt , things from ...
What do you want to believe ?
I want some kind of explanation .
Well , isn 't it obvious ?
I 'm a witch .
I 'm not finding this very amusing .
Norman , I only have so many answers . Take your choice .
What do you mean ?
Are you trying to tell me that you 've been attempting witchcraft ?
I can 't believe it . Why ?
How did you ever begin ?
Does it matter , Norman ?
Yes ! And knowing what you do about its background ?
Well , when you say it like that , of course it sounds ridiculous .
Ridiculous ? It 's stupid !
But , Norman , when you want things to happen or not to happen
to someone you love .
Oh , Norman , the things I did . They seem to work .
What things ?
At least , most of the time .
Don 't you see the very exceptions
prove the things you were doing didn 't work ?
There were other evil forces working against us !
I can 't believe it !
A woman of your intelligence .
Is this the way you 've been spending your time at the cottage ?
And I thought that you were ...
I 'm sorry . You must 've been very bored .
Darling ...
Now look at all that .
You can 't be serious about it .
From the moment we arrived here we 've been faced
- with such hostility from the faculty . - Hostility ?
Yes ! Their hatred and their petty jealousy .
- I was afraid they would destroy us . - Tansy .
You 're imagining these things . What 's got into you ?
Is this some kind of a joke ?
Norman , I feel very strongly about this .
Well , when did this all start ? And why ?
Two years ago in Jamaica .
When you almost died in that terrible accident .
You were dying , Norman .
The doctors had given you up .
I was frantic , desperate .
I kept saying to myself over and over ,
" Let me die in his place . Oh , dear Lord , let me die in his place . "
And then , suddenly , I thought of Carubius .
And of the time we watched him bring a young girl back to life .
Whom the entire village thought dead .
[ Norman ] That girl was in a trance .
No , Norman !
A catatonic trance !
She was ice cold , Norman . Dead .
And then ...
Remember we saw ... We saw the girl 's mother and Carubius stand over her .
And her mother cried out ,
" Take me , I am old . She is young , let her live . "
And Carubius worked his spell ,
and the old woman died .
And when she died , the girl opened up her eyes .
She began to breathe again .
I thought of that moment , Norman .
I was willing to die to save you .
But you 're here and very much alive .
I know , but you regained consciousness . I didn 't have to use it .
But I know , Norman , without a shadow of a doubt that it would 've worked .
And I was so desperate . I was ready to try it !
I 'm sure you 're convinced I 'm quite insane .
I 'm not convinced about anything .
And if we were to investigate all the strange rituals
performed by women based on their so called intuition ,
half the female population would be in asylums .
I don 't know what to think .
All right .
It may have worked then , but there 's certainly no need to use it now .
- Yes , there is , Norman ... - Give it up !
- No ! No , Norman ! - You understand ? Completely !
Norman , I will not be responsible for what happens to us
if you make me give up my protection !
Tansy , for God 's sake ! Protections for what ?
Oh , so everything you 've got out of life is just the result of your ability , is it ?
Last night I was your good luck charm ...
Look , I 'm not arguing with you !
And you think everyone loves you here at Hempnell , don 't you ?
Well , let me tell you something .
That faculty would 've seen you dead a long time ago if they could 've managed it !
Now stop it ! You 're being hysterical !
- No , I 'm not ! I 'm telling the truth ! - Just because you 're ...
Insane ?
Oh , Norman .
[ crying ] Oh , Norman , I love you so much .
I know . I know .
Oh , Norman . What should I do ?
What should I do ?
Are you sure that 's everything ?
You 've had me tear up the whole house , haven 't you ?
[ gasps ] Norman , your picture ! Norman !
No , no , not your picture !
Tansy ! Tansy !
No , Norman , not your picture ! Norman ! No !
Norman , not your picture ! No !
Oh , no !
[ mouthing ] No .
Don 't you sense something , Norman ?
[ screeching ]
[ phone ringing ]
Hello . Hello .
[ woman breathing heavily ]
Hello , who 's there ?
[ woman ] Don 't you know who this is ?
Haven 't you been waiting ?
Look , who is this ?
Oh , it 's been such torture waiting for this moment ,
knowing that soon ... Soon I 'd hear your voice again .
And I 'd hear you whisper , " I love you . "
What ?
Come to me and take me in your arms .
Oh , Norman . Norman ...
I need you .
Norman , don 't you know who this is ?
No , I do not !
After all you 've done to me .
After you 've undressed me with your eyes a hundred ...
[ dramatic music playing ]
Who was that ?
Nobody . It was the wrong number .
Did you burn everything ?
Yes . Everything .
Wake up , you bloody fool !
This is a restricted area . You 're not supposed to be doing 60 !
I wasn 't doin ' no 60 , neither !
- Yes , you were ! - I shan 't stop for you next time .
[ Flora ] Norman !
Are you all right ?
Oh , yes , I 'm all right .
I could 've sworn nothing was coming .
Fool . He might 've killed you .
How 's Tansy ?
She 's fine .
She seemed a bit under Friday night .
She 's probably worried about her no trump bid .
She needn 't be . I think she plays extremely well .
[ woman on PA ] Attention , please ! Will Mrs. Carr come to her office immediately ?
Will Mrs. Carr come to her office immediately ?
Sounds like trouble .
- Thank you . - Not a very good start for a new week .
No . Must hurry . I 'm late .
I think it 's about time we got a few things straightened out , Taylor .
I agree .
You can start by apologizing for your behavior on Friday .
Start by apologizing ?
Look here , I know what you 're trying to do to me .
Why you recommended I be removed from your course ?
Why you continually fail all my test papers ?
I fail your test papers when you submit them
because they 're simply not good enough .
And I recommended transferring you
because I thought your antagonism towards me , conscious or otherwise ,
has prevented you from doing any serious work .
- Hello . Lab please . - Well , that 's one way out of it .
- If it helps salve your conscience . - Now watch it !
You deliberately base your tests on lectures I 've missed !
Attending lectures is your responsibility .
I can only teach , I can 't absorb the knowledge for you .
Hello , Bates .
Will you get me those two slides for this afternoon 's lecture ?
All right , thanks .
You 've discriminated against me from the moment
- I began dating Margaret Abbott . - I 've what ?
You 've influenced the other professors against me .
Anything to have me thrown out of college
so that you could have Margaret to yourself !
Do you realize the seriousness of such a disgusting accusation ?
- It is disgusting ! - Get out !
At first I was willing to give you the benefit of the doubt ,
but on Saturday night , when I told her how much I loved her ...
- Saturday night ? - She suddenly pushed me aside .
Started whimpering your name !
She was crying ! And then I knew .
She laughed at me .
Taunted me with all the sordid details of your nasty , little affair .
Get out .
You better reconsider , Taylor , and fast .
I want those passing grades I deserve .
Perhaps the dean would be interested in my story .
Come in , Harold .
Did you hear any of that ?
What you mean , you and Jennings ?
Hmm .
No . Another matter , and quite serious .
It concerns you and Margaret Abbott .
Margaret ? She 's certainly in the limelight this morning .
This can 't be treated lightly , Norman .
She 's in Flora Carr 's office at this moment .
In a dangerously hysterical state .
She claims you 've violated her .
I 've what ? Harold ...
- She must be mad . - Possibly .
But we 've got to handle this carefully .
Remember , she 's Flora 's ward .
You better come with me .
Do you realize the enormity of this accusation against
Professor Taylor , Margaret ?
I thought a great deal before coming to you
but I had to tell the truth . I 'm frightened .
Harold 's told you everything ?
Margaret ...
Look at me , Margaret .
When was all this supposed to have happened ?
[ Margaret ] Saturday night .
On Saturday night I was at home with my wife .
And I suppose she 'll share your lie to help save your precious reputation .
Is this the way you repay kindness and attention ?
Kindness ! Attention ! They 're just words to hide the truth .
And I 've always respected you .
Kindness and attention from a teacher to a student , and nothing more .
You were with Bill Jennings on Saturday night , weren 't you ?
- That 's a lie ! - He was making love to you .
That 's right .
Try to pretend I 'm the kind of girl who gives her favors to everyone .
He 's just told me you were with him .
All right . I was with him .
But we weren 't making love .
Don 't you remember what you told me ?
No one else must touch me .
No one else must touch me !
Control yourself !
[ phone ringing ]
Professor Carr here .
Well , can 't it wait ?
Very well .
The dean .
Better come with me , Norman .
I 'm staying here .
It 's imperative . It 's about this matter .
[ Flora ] We shan 't be a moment .
I 'm telling the truth !
- Coming ? - I won 't be long .
The dean wants us now , Norman .
I won 't be long !
It 's no good going on with it now .
You could see the state Miss Abbott is in .
- You phoned me on Saturday night , didn 't you ? - It 's a lie !
You made a disgusting proposition .
And when I was about to hang up , you used vile language .
Vile and filthy !
And this from someone that I sincerely admired .
Well , I didn 't know what I was doing ! I didn 't know .
I didn 't know .
Something came over me , I ...
[ crying ] I had to call you . I had to .
Margaret .
I hate you .
[ wind howling ]
I 've spoken to the dean about you .
Bill ...
And he agrees that ...
That you were treated unfairly .
What about Margaret ?
Was she treated unfairly ?
Margaret 's confessed that the whole thing was a lie .
A lie ?
Everything 's a lie to you , isn 't it , Taylor ?
You 're very familiar with lies .
That 's all you really know how to do , is teach lies .
You like teaching girls , don 't you ?
I 've watched you , we 've all watched you .
You 're very successful at teaching people how to lie .
[ crying ]
Mr. Gunnison ...
Harold , get over here quickly , will you ?
I 've got Jennings here . Yes , he 's just tried to threaten me with a gun .
No , no one 's hurt .
Yeah .
You think you 'll get away with it , don 't you ?
I 'll spread the truth about you . I 'll see that it gets out !
You won 't get away with what you did to Margaret .
You won 't be able to lie your way out of it this time , Mr. Taylor .
[ Tansy ] I tell you , Norman ,
I will not be responsible for what happens to us
if you make me give up my protections .
[ thunder clapping ]
- Norman ? - Oh , hi .
Something 's happened .
Happened ?
Something has happened .
No , nothing 's happened .
What is that ?
I don 't know .
Oh !
It 's a recording of a lecture I gave in Manchester last month .
I want you to hear this .
Who sent it ?
I don 't know . The dean , I suppose .
There 's no signature on it .
It 's on official notepaper , isn 't it ?
Don 't play it , Norman .
Now , don 't start again .
Norman , please . For my sake !
Tansy , I 'm playing it for your sake .
Norman , please !
[ Norman ] You find in certain neurosis there is a danger of temporary relief .
Neurosis based on rejection , frustration , lack of love ,
loneliness makes the subject pursue strange occupations which are inexplicable
to the adjusted mind .
Well , to begin with , superstition .
A working definition might be misguided , unobjective science .
More simply , the morbid desire to escape from reality .
It is a science devoid of all empirical values .
A science completely based on a priori evaluation .
Upon investigation into the origins of most superstitions ,
it is found that in the main they 're derived from
beliefs in primitive states of culture .
- They 've ceased to be part of ritual practice ... - [ clattering ]
... and have merely become irrational beliefs , exercising no useful function ...
The superstition that spilling salt brings bad luck
- dates from the time when it was believed that ... - [ shrill tone ringing ]
... partaking of salt was considered protection against
evil spirits , witchcraft and other evil influences .
And the fact that there are a number of superstitions connected with mirrors
is derived from the belief that a man 's soul is visible ...
What are you doing ?
What 's the matter with you ?
Oh , I have a headache . I guess I better get an aspirin .
There 's something I want you to hear .
- No . - I 'll keep it down low ...
- Norman , no . - Why not ?
Oh , you 're so blind . So blind !
What does it take to convince you ?
Come over here , Tansy , I want to talk to you .
Why ? So you can give me the benefit of your brilliant logic ?
[ ringing ]
Don 't answer it .
Hello ?
Hang up !
[ shrill tone ringing ]
Hang up , Norman !
Control yourself !
[ groaning ]
Oh , no .
[ thudding ]
Norman , don 't open the door !
Norman , please !
[ Tansy ] The phone . Where 's the phone ?
[ Norman ] Oh , blast !
Norman , don 't open the door !
[ wind howling ]
[ thunder clapping ]
I 'm not going to say that I think there was something out there , Norman .
I know that 's what you expect me to say , isn 't it ?
Yes . Yes . I mean , it was just a coincidence .
The tape and the phone call just got on my nerves . That 's all .
And the storm just happened to blow out the lights .
You see , I 'm not so bad , am I ?
I think we could do with a drink , don 't you ?
Let me die in his place .
Hear me ? Let me die in his place .
What ? Did you say something , darling ?
Oh ! How about a drink , darling ?
You don 't think I 've drunk enough , do you ?
- No . - I 'm nearly falling asleep .
No , one more won 't hurt . Here .
What about you ?
I 'll share yours .
Here 's to you .
To us , Norman .
Here . Have some more .
A little more . A little more .
There . A little more .
What are you trying to do ? Make me drunk ? Huh ?
Pretty sneaky , we women . Drink up , darling . Here .
That 's enough .
[ coughing ]
Hey , hey , hey , easy does it .
Now we 're joined in spirit , Norman .
A very special spirit .
Very special .
[ Tansy echoing ] Norman ! Norman !
Norman , all that is mine is yours , Norman .
And all that is yours is mine .
Everything you have is mine .
You 'll give it to me without hindrance
and of your own free choice .
All that you have is mine , Norman .
Say it . Say it .
All I have
is yours .
All that you have is mine .
[ Norman groaning ]
[ gasps ]
Oh , no .
Uh , mmm ...
Tansy .
[ Tansy on tape ] This is goodbye , my darling .
It 's really the only way for me .
Loving you as deeply as I do .
It 's the only way to defeat the horror that attempted to destroy you last night .
Yes , I shall die in your place .
You have so much to offer this world .
I 've gone away so that this terrible curse can no longer touch you .
And by midnight it will be finished .
Over .
There is nothing you can do , Norman . Nothing .
Oh , I do love you .
I love you .
[ recording ends ]
There is nothing you can do , Norman . Nothing .
Oh , I do love you .
I love you .
[ car approaching ]
- Tan ... - Are you all right ?
- Hilda . - I 've been trying to phone you all the morning
but your phone 's out of order .
We 've got a meeting in the dean 's office .
That 's why I 'm here . I said I 'd let you know .
Hilda , have you seen Tansy ?
There is something wrong .
Harold saw Tansy this morning getting onto the coach .
He thought she was going to the cottage .
- The cottage ? - Said she seemed upset .
It 's that dreadful Abbott girl .
I 'm surprised Tansy believed any of it .
She ought to be put in a rest home .
The Abbott girl , that is .
[ Tansy ] I tell you , Norman , I will not be responsible for what happens to us
if you make me give up my protections .
I shall die in your place , my darling .
I shall die in your place .
By midnight it will be finished .
Over .
There is nothing you can do . Nothing .
[ honking horn ]
Tansy !
[ continues honking horn ]
Hi there . Are you okay ?
Yes , I 'm all right .
Come on , chump .
Me and my mate here , we seen you okay .
We thought you was passing . Plenty of time to pass .
[ groaning ] I was trying to signal my wife .
She was on that bus .
You were lucky all the way , mister .
Anyhow , the damage don 't seem too bad .
The suspension 's gone though .
I must get going .
Mister , the only place you got to get going is the doctor .
I 'm all right .
Look , you may be all right outside ,
but maybe you got internal injuries .
Yes . Do you know where I can get a hired car ?
Give me a lift in your truck .
Look , mister , the first thing you gotta do is make us some papers , huh ?
All right , say the whole thing 's my fault .
Company rule , mister . It ain 't going to take long .
Tansy !
[ echoing ] Tansy !
Oh ...
[ panting ]
" In the house of the dead in the place of the dead . "
[ owl hooting ]
[ grunts ]
[ door creaking ]
[ bell tolling ]
[ Norman sobbing ]
Oh , darling ...
Your wife 's certainly in a very bad state of shock . Not reacting at all .
What really happened ?
We had an accident .
[ doctor ] As long as you hold back information from me ,
I 'm afraid there isn 't much ...
I told you , we had an accident .
All right , you had an accident . It may be true .
I 'm not a psychiatrist , but I 've been dealing with people for a long time ,
and I can usually tell when they 're trying to hide something .
And you 're trying to hide something from me . What is it ?
Why has your wife been in the sea since the accident ?
She 's so clammy . Clothes damp , smell of the sea on them .
I don 't want to interfere with your job ,
but your wife may be in a very serious condition .
The very thing you 're withholding could be the key to her recovery .
All right . I don 't know how to explain this .
[ Tansy ] No .
Tansy . What is it ?
Tell nothing .
Tansy , I don 't understand .
Take me home !
Your wife 's in no condition to go anywhere except to a hospital .
I 'll call for an ambulance .
No , I 'm going to take her home .
The decision 's yours to make , of course .
But I must remind you her condition may be worse than we both think .
By not telling the truth and authorizing immediate confinement ,
you could be taking away her one chance of recovery .
I hope you know what you 're doing .
[ operator ] Number , please .
Operator ? Connect me with the General Hospital .
No !
Tansy , what are you doing out of bed ?
Norman , I 'm all right . Really , I am .
Oh , darling , you look awful . You must 've had a terrible time .
You don 't remember ? Anything ?
It was like a nightmare .
A terrible nightmare .
I remember being pulled out into the water .
Deeper and deeper .
I kept calling out for help .
I kept crying out for help , Norman . No one heard me .
No one heard me .
Oh , I 'm so tired .
Yes . Come on up . Come on , I 'm going to take you back to bed .
Come on .
[ dramatic music playing ]
Is this what you 're looking for ?
[ chuckling ] Oh , why , Norman ...
I thought you were a burglar .
What have you there ?
Oh , it 's a candid snap I took last week .
Now , it 's ruined .
Never mind , I have the negative . I 'll make another ...
Or was it this ?
What is it ?
A rather unique recording .
What sort of recording ?
Let 's hear it . Shall we ?
[ Norman ] You find in certain neurosis there is a danger of temporary release .
Neurosis based on rejection , frustration , lack of love ,
loneliness , it makes the subject pursue strange occupations
which are inexplicable to the adjusted mind .
Well , to begin with , superstition .
Working definition might be , misguided , unobjective science .
More simply , the morbid desire to escape from reality .
- It is a science ... - [ shrill tone ringing ]
What 's the matter , Flora ? Does it bother you ?
No . It simply began to get on my nerves .
That 's all .
And what about my nerves ? And Tansy 's ?
- Why , whatever are you talking about , Norman ? - Why did you hypnotize her ?
Why did you try to drive her out of her mind ?
[ laughing ]
Am I amusing you ?
Yes , you are , Norman .
I knew you were naive ,
but I didn 't know you were as naive as all that .
After all that 's happened .
You mean to tell me that you still put it down to natural causes ?
There 's nothing unnatural or supernatural about hypnosis .
You 're behaving like a frightened schoolboy , Norman .
Frightened of being wrong .
And you ... You are wrong .
I did not hypnotize Tansy .
She attempted to kill me tonight , under your influence .
Isn 't that a bit absurd ?
Why should I do such a thing ?
Why should I want to kill you ?
Yes , why ? I know you 've resented us from the beginning .
Resented everything we stood for ,
and that resentment 's turned into hatred , hasn 't it ?
A hatred which has made you lose all reason . Yes , I can see that .
Or was it because of your precious Margaret ?
Do you believe that I raped her ?
Fear . Fear of losing your position here .
Fear of someone younger taking your place .
And you knew Tansy was emotionally upset and you used it .
It wasn 't difficult to work on her imagination . On her weakness .
Knowing that if my wife was proved insane I was finished here !
But a logical mind like yours would be strong enough to prevent any interference !
No , Norman ! You protest too much !
Why does it upset you so much to think that there 's such a thing
in this world as witchcraft ?
It 's one of the oldest religions in the world .
It just depends on what you believe in .
There 's an explanation for everything in science .
[ laughing ] Oh , really . Such tenacity .
Any theory , however improbable , wild , and coincidental ,
so long as it fits into your tidy view of things .
What 're you doing ?
What about the accident with the truck , Norman ?
What truck ?
Yes , isn 't it odd that I should know about it ?
How does your Aristotelian mind account for that ?
Don 't be ridiculous . The papers could 've got hold of it .
They didn 't .
[ Norman ] What are you doing ?
Preparing to prove something .
Preparing to prove , my dear Norman ,
that you really do believe in magic .
These , as you can see , are tarot cards .
You know their significance , of course . They represent your home .
And this , of course , will represent Tansy .
There ...
Now !
You stupid woman !
Do you honestly think that I believe any of that rubbish ?
Yes , it does seem like nonsense , doesn 't it ?
Just a silly woman setting fire to some cards .
[ screeching ]
Stop it !
But why ? You don 't really believe in this , Norman .
You couldn 't be concerned over a few bits of burning paper .
Just a woman 's eccentricity .
It 's too late to help Tansy .
Or is it all in your mind , Norman ?
Are you imagining things ?
Do you really believe your home is burning ?
Will you ever know , Norman ?
Will you ever be sure ?
Is your house on fire ?
Is Tansy dying ?
You 're raving mad .
[ laughing ]
[ grunts ]
Burn , witch , burn .
[ Norman chattering on tape ]
[ Norman ] On investigation into the origins of most superstitions ,
it is found that in the main they 're derived from beliefs
in primitive states of culture .
They 've ceased to be part of ritual practice ,
and have merely become irrational beliefs ...
exercising no useful function ...
[ shrill tone ringing ]
Norman !
[ squawking ]
[ screaming ]
[ coughing ]
Norman !
[ Norman chattering on tape ]
And then they are no longer really taken seriously .
[ shrill tone ringing ]
[ eagle squawking ]
[ screaming ]
[ rattling ]
What 's going on around here ?
I 've just seen Norman tearing across the college grounds like a man possessed .
What are you doing with this ?
Oh , just running Norman 's speech , that 's all .
Do you realize you 've got it switched through onto the public address system ?
It 's booming out all over the grounds .
Really ? How silly of me .
- I never could work ... - No , no ...
[ Norman chattering loudly ]
[ shrill tone ringing ]
[ silence ]
Flora , what are you doing ?
[ tape recorder stops ]
I 'm sorry , Lindsay .
I imagine I 've been working too hard .
I 've been trying to tell you that for a long time .
I knew , dear . Quite right .
Perhaps we 'll take a trip .
Why are you looking at me like that , Lindsay ?
Is something wrong ?
No , I don 't believe so .
You 're rather pale and your hands are trembling .
What are you troubled about , Flora ?
Nothing .
I 'm merely exhausted , that 's all .
Let 's go , shall we ?
Oh , by the way , Gunnison tells me
they 've decided who to give the chair to .
Oh ? Harvey , I suppose .
No . I thought it would be Harvey ,
but the dean changed his mind .
It 's going to Norman Taylor .
I doubt that .
What do you mean ?
Nothing . Except that the dean will probably change his mind again .
Wait a minute , you 're not goin ' in there !
My wife 's in there !
Norman ! Norman !
Norman !
- Darling ! - Thank God .
- Are you all right ? - Yes , yes .
What happened ?
The fireman said it was the oil stove .
[ Lindsay ] Norman may be a bit young ,
but he 's a good man , don 't you agree ?
Oh , yes . A very good man indeed .
Who the deuce has left the door open at this time of night ?
Come away , Lindsay . Don 't go in there .
Let the caretaker worry about that .
Well , there 's no excuse for this sort of thing and I shall report it .
Lindsay !
[ screaming ]
Flora ! Flora !
Flora !